PAOLO VIVIANI

PhD - Senior Researcher

♥ Torino, ITALY

@ paolo.vivi@gmail.com

% paoloviviani.github.io





PROFILE

I'm a theoretical physicist turned computer scientist with 5+ years of applied research experience in the field of HPC and ML/DL. My goal is to use supercomputers (including several TOP500 and two top 10 machines) to solve scientific and engineering problems, like developing and training machine learning models at scale. I'm also interested in developing algorithms to exploit the potential of near-term quantum computers, and to investigate their interactions with classical HPC.

I've been involved in several funded research projects with different responsibilties, mostly as a principal technical contact point for a partner, and task leader.



EDUCATION

Ph.D., Computer Science

University of Torino

2015 - 2019

♥ Torino, IT

Thesis: Deep Learning at Scale with Nearest Neighbours Communications. Supervisor: Marco Aldinucci. Funded by Noesis Solutions.

Master's Degree, Theoretical physics

University of Torino, 104/110

♥ Collegio Universitario "R. Einaudi", Torino

Scholarship winner: "Piano Lauree Scientifiche 2008", granted by Società Italiana di Fisica.



EXPERIENCE

LINKS Foundation

Senior Researcher, Advanced Computing

2021 - present

♥ Torino, IT

- HPC, Machine Learning and Big Data convergence acceleration of scientific/technical applications
- Quantum algorithms and applications discrete optimization on neutral atoms machines and quantum annealers
- ML/DL algorithms for neural signal decoding
- Funded research projects proposals writing, technical management and execution
- ETP4HPC Working groups member

Noesis Solutions

Reasearch Engineer

2015 - 2021

- Novara, IT
- · Machine learning methodologies for engineering modelling and design exploration
- Development of numerical code and software stack
- Supervisor of one internship
- Technical contact for funded research projects

MAIN INTERESTS

High Performance Computing

Machine Learning



Quantum software and algorithms



SKILLS

Parallel Computing Quantum Computing Machine Learning Research project management Cloud technologies



Programming

C++ Python CUDA Fortran Git



Soft

Presentations Communication of results Formalization of requirements Decomposition of problems



Tools

- Keras
- MxNet Pandas
- BLAS/Lapack
- MPI/OpenMP
- Dask
- PBS/Slurm
- Qiskit

Docker

- Openstack
- Gitlab CI Linux
- IP Networking
- Latex
- CISCO CCNA course completed in 2008.



Italian

English



French



RESEARCH ACTIVITY

Funded Research Projects

See paoloviviani.github.io/projects for full list and details.

| B-CRATOS | ± H2020-FET Open | 🗎 2021 - ongoing |
|-----------------|------------------|----------------------|
| ACROSS | ± H2020-EuroHPC | 🛗 2021 – ongoing |
| Lexis | <u> </u> | 2021 - 2022 |
| BoSS | | |
| Fortissimo 2 | | ≅ 2016 − 2018 |
| CloudFlow | FP7-I4MS project | 2016 - 2017 |
| MACH | <u>m</u> ITEA2 | 2015 - 2016 |
| | | |

Selected Publications

See paoloviviani.github.io/publications for full list.

- 1. Scionti, A. et al. Distributed HPC Resources Orchestration for Supporting Large-Scale Workflow Execution in HPC, Big Data, and AI Convergence Towards Exascale: Challenge and Vision First, 23 (CRC Press, New York, Jan. 2022).
- Reniers, V. et al. Authenticated and Auditable Data Sharing via Smart Contract in (Association for Computing Machinery, Brno, Czech Republic, 2020), 324-331.
- Reniers, V. et al. Analysis of Architectural Variants for Auditable Blockchainbased Private Data Sharing in Proceedings of the 34th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium on Applied Computing (ACM, Limassol, Cyprus, 2019), 346-354.
- 4. Viviani, P., Drocco, M., Baccega, D., Colonnelli, I. & Aldinucci, M. Deep Learning at Scale in Proc. of 27th Euromicro Intl. Conference on Parallel Distributed and network-based Processing (PDP) (IEEE, Pavia, Italy, 2019), 124-131.
- 5. Aldinucci, M. et al. HPC4AI, an AI-on-demand federated platform endeavour in ACM Computing Frontiers (Ischia, Italy, May 2018).
- Tordini, F., Aldinucci, M., Viviani, P., Merelli, I. & Liò, P. Scientific Workflows on Clouds with Heterogeneous and Preemptible Instances in Proc. of the Intl. Conference on Parallel Computing, ParCo 2017, 12-15 September 2017, Bologna, Italy (IOS Press, 2018).
- Viviani, P., Drocco, M. & Aldinucci, M. Scaling Dense Linear Algebra on Multicore and Beyond: a Survey in Proc. of 26th Euromicro Intl. Conference on Parallel Distributed and network-based Processing (PDP) (IEEE, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 2018).
- 8. Viviani, P., Torquati, M., Aldinucci, M. & d'Ippolito, R. Multiple back-end support for the Armadillo linear algebra interface in In proc. of the 32nd ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC) (Marrakesh, Morocco, Apr. 2017), 1566-

Other

- Co-supervisor of one M.Sc. Thesis
- Over 35 conference and journal papers reviewed
- Four PhD schools attended.
- Program Committee member, Euromicro International Conference on Parallel, Distributed, and Network-based Processing (PDP) for 2018 (also session chair), 2019 and 2020.
- Program Committee member, Parallel Numerical Methods and Libraries for Heterogeneous Multi/Manycores (PDP2018 and PDP2019).
- Program Committee member, Artifact Evaluation, Euro-Par 2018
- Program Committee member, 16th IEEE International Conference on Scalable Computing and Communications (ScalCom 2016).

***** FREE TIME

Avid traveller and photographer. Former track & field athlete, now turned to playground basketball.

paoloviviani.github.io/portfolio

Photographer

OASIS Project

2013

♦ Kharga, Egypt

Archaeological expedition funded by Fondazione Collegio delle Università Milanesi and American University in Cairo.

Photographer

Collegio Universitario "R. Einaudi"

Exchange student

Tauranga Boy's College

2006

▼ Tauranga, New Zealand

Scuba Diver

PADI Advanced Open Water Diver

From 2004

Track and Field athlete

Javelin Throw - Regional and National competitions

1997 - 2012

Volunteer

IAAF Athletics World Championship

2009

♥ Berlin, Germany

English Course

'General English Super Intensive' C1 level course at Alpha College of English

2012

Dublin, Ireland

I authorize the use of my personal data in accordance with Italian Privacy Protection Law (30/06/2003, n.196/03), and GDPR (UE 2016/679)